<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Sermon disswading obloquie against governours preached on Sunday Decemb. 7, 1662 in a solemne audience, and now, at the request of divers that heard it, made publick / by William Haywood.</title>
            <author>Haywood, William, 1599 or 1600-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25425</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08951808</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08951808</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42087</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43139)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42087)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1286:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Sermon disswading obloquie against governours preached on Sunday Decemb. 7, 1662 in a solemne audience, and now, at the request of divers that heard it, made publick / by William Haywood.</title>
                  <author>Haywood, William, 1599 or 1600-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for R. Royston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of speech --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Subversive activities --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42087:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42087:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Diſſwading from OBLOQUIE AGAINST Governours; Preached on Sunday <hi>Decemb.</hi> 7. 1662. in a Solemne <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DIENCE;</hi> And now, at the requeſt of divers that heard it, made publick.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM HAYVVOOD, Doctor in Divinity, Chaplain in Ordinary to His <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> and Rector of S. <hi>Giles's in the Fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Pet. 2.10.</bibl>
               <p>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Book-ſeller to His moſt SACRED MAJESTY. 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:42087:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42087:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ACTS 23. ver. 5.</bibl>
                  <p>—<hi>For it is written, Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have read you a Text, which, if duly conſidered and made conſcience of, might help to abate much the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemence of thoſe Fires which late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threatned the common ſafety. For betwixt wicked Thoughts againſt our Rulers, (Thoughts, the fountain of Sedition) and rebellious Deeds (Deeds, the flame that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh Sedition, and conſume a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) Words are the readieſt Inſtruments; Words the bellows that kindle the Sparkles; Words the wind that ventilate the Flame:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42087:3"/>were it not for which, the Fire might eaſily languiſh and expire of it ſelf. So that no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good ſervice might be done, in quieting firſt the Tongues of the Multitude, that their Hearts and their Hands might return to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter temper.</p>
            <p>To which purpoſe I have choſen this Scripture, as a means to convince the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of numbers, touching the hainouſneſſe of evil ſpeaking againſt their Governours. For nothing more undoeth the common ſort, then an opinion that ſuch talk is but light prattle; no great danger or crime in it. Hence ſuch clouds, ſuch ſwarmes of lies and flanders, which, like the Flies and Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> have covered ſome parts of this Land, till they have darkened it again, and made it noyſome. Though all ſins abound; yet ſo as detraction and ſpightful lying, not any abounds. Of all enormities leaſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is made of Slander; and of all ſlanders, leaſt of ſlandering our Rulers. As if there were utterly no Law for the Tongue; as if Slander were not the crime that hunted Chriſt to his death, and his moſt faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant our late Soveraign: As if there were no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42087:3"/>curſe on the Whiſperer and double-tongued; or as if the greater and higher any fame were, the more mens mouths were priviledged to bark againſt it. So free, ſo licentious all of all ſorts, in a manner, to vent their gall at their lips, that in no one reſpect more thoſe words of the 14. <hi>Pſalm</hi> appear verified; <hi>Their throat is an open ſepulchre, the poyſon of aſpes is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lips: their mouths full of curſing and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now though divers Scriptures might be found to curb this miſchief, yet I have thought on this, as in ſundry reſpects effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual. 1. Becauſe it takes ſtrength from both Teſtaments, the Old and the New, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found here, and in <hi>Exodus</hi> 22.28. and ſo not to be rejected by <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile, Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>Mahometan.</hi> 2. Becauſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> quoteth this Text as forcible againſt himſelf, in behalf of <hi>Ananias</hi> the High Prieſt. <hi>Ananias</hi> a wicked man, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> a holy man; yet not a holy man allowed to reproch a wicked man in authority. 3. Becauſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was juſt, and ſuch as toward an equal might be warranted; yet not to be defended toward the high Prieſt, a chief Ruler of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42087:4"/>people. To which if ye ſhall adde, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was groſly injured, and multitudes of our Railers never injured; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> one that had power to curſe, our Revilers no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; <hi>Ananias</hi> not a lawful Governour, ours both lawfull and highly meriting; Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s ill language true, &amp; defendable by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, our peoples falſe, and utterly againſt Scripture: Theſe things conſidered (one would think) might aſſwage much this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular diſeaſe of railing upon Dignities, the liberty whereof hath once already, and may, who knoweth how ſoon? again (if God in mercy prevent it not) overturn this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>We proceed to a diviſion of the words, which appear to branch themſelves into three main parts: 1. An abuſe forbidden, <hi>Evil ſpeaking:</hi> 2. The parties towards whom for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, <hi>Rulers of the people:</hi> 3. The perſons forbidden to <hi>ſpeak evil;</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> applies it to himſelf, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil;</hi> and if S. <hi>Paul</hi> may not, then not any man. To han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle theſe in the plaineſt order, will be as the words ſtand in the Original; and begin firſt with the Parties againſt whom evil may not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42087:4"/>be ſpoken, by pointing out, 1. Who are theſe <hi>Rulers of the people:</hi> 2. Who the <hi>Parties</hi> that may not ſpeak evil; neither Saint <hi>Paul</hi> nor any man: 3. The Abuſe it ſelf, by ſhewing what this <hi>evil ſpeaking</hi> here is, and why forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And of theſe, by God's help, in their order: beginning firſt with the parties againſt whom evil may not be ſpoken, <hi>viz. The Rulers of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſuch difficult Charge this a ppeares: Firſt, in that it is laid Negative. Negatives are eaſier obeyed then Affirmatives: for not to doe, requires no labour. Then, that it is a Negative, not of Thoughts, or Deeds, but of Words. Words are not hard to refrain. Little can he doe, that cannot hold his tongue. Nor, thirdly, a Negative of good words,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.3.</note> ſuch as <hi>David</hi> thought it grievous to forbear (<hi>I kept ſilence even from good words, but it was pain and grief to me:</hi>) but a Reſtraint of bad words onely, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil.</hi> Nor that Reſtraint general, <hi>ſpeak evil of none:</hi> but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, <hi>not of our Governours,</hi> which are but few, and the world wide enough beſides, for our tongues to be bold with; <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy people.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42087:5"/>
            <p> The Ruler, who is he? The Text in <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> hath two ſeveral nouns joyned with two divers Verbs: <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Rulers of thy people.</hi> By the <hi>Gods</hi> ſome would have meant <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Governours,</hi> and by <hi>Rulers,</hi> the <hi>temporal Magiſtrate:</hi> but the Text favours not this; for S. <hi>Paul</hi> takes the latter <hi>Noun,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they ſay ſignifies the <hi>temporal Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> &amp; applieth it to the <hi>High Prieſt; Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler.</hi> So that <hi>Ruler</hi> is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied indifferently of both. Some would have them differ as <hi>Princeps factus,</hi> and <hi>Princeps natus,</hi> Rulers that were made Rulers, and Rulers born ſo. Made Rulers; ſuch were the Judges: <hi>Judges and Officers ſhalt thou make thee in all thy gates,</hi> Deut. 16.18. Rulers that were born Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; ſuch were the Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> eldeſt in deſcent from the Patriarchs, called <hi>Heads of the houſes of their fathers, Princes of the tribes,</hi> Nu. 7.2. Ye ſhall find theſe born Rulers firſt mentiond <hi>Exo.</hi> 16.22. and thoſe made ones two Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters after, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.25. And whether of theſe were ſuperiour it greatly matters not. Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient it is for us to know, they were both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſupreme Governour; both to be reverenced in their degree, and evil tongues
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42087:5"/>to walk againſt neither: neither againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Judges, made Rulers by their Office; nor againſt the Heads of the Tribes, born Rulers by deſcent: neither againſt Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Governours, the Prieſts and Levites, who were among the Jews a kind of born Rulers; nor againſt the ſecular Magiſtrates, appointed to bear the Sword under the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power; and much leſs againſt the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power it ſelf. 'Tis hard to ſever theſe in honour or in diſhonour, in a well-framed Community. 'Tis an injury toward the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to vilifie his Deputy; a reproch to the King himſelf, to ſay He hath evil Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours about him. And he that diſparageth a Prince, as weak and unable to judge of good Counſel, through him diſparages his chief Counſellours and Officers; yea, and all the people under his Government, inaſmuch as the diſgrace of the Head redounds to the whole Body.</p>
            <p>Both are injured by ſuch evil ſpeaking: but of the two, they moſt that ſit higheſt; ſpecially they that are both wayes Rulers, by deſcent and by office, <hi>Principes nati &amp; Principes facti</hi> both, who have ſupreme overſight of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42087:6"/>both Powers, Eccleſiaſtick and Secular, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had; from whom lieth no appeal, and upon whom the cares of all are laid. Theſe, above all, are exempted from the fury of bad tongues: Speak not evil of theſe in any wiſe.</p>
            <p>Neither of theſe, nor yet of their inferiour Officers, even for their ſakes: For as they help to bear the burthen with their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, they make but one body, and draw one common yoke. Neither higher there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nor lower Powers may be reviled; no not the Prieſts and Levites, as far as they are intereſted <hi>in regimine,</hi> in ruling the people. And ſome way they are intereſted: for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls them <hi>Leaders of the blind, Lights of them that ſit in darkneſs, Inſtructers of the fooliſh:</hi> and ſpeaks it even of Jewiſh Teachers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.19. Leſs then whom we cannot imagine the Diſciples of Chriſt to be, whom our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour terms the <hi>light of the world,</hi> Mat. 5.14. And though ſome of late dayes will not abide to hear they ſhould have any rule, yet we know where Saint <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth Chriſtian Congregations, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.37.</note> 
               <hi>and ſubmit your ſelves,</hi> Heb. 13.17. After
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42087:6"/>which preſently follows, <hi>For they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give an account, &amp;c.</hi> And who are thoſe watchmen over your ſouls, but the Clergy? <hi>Let a man ſo eſteem of us as the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the myſteries of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.1. Stewards, I trow, are Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. If any doubt it, hearken to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>Who then is that faithfull and wiſe ſteward, whom his Lord ſhall make ruler over his houſhold, to give them their meat in due ſeaſon?</hi> Luke 12.42. I contend not for their power, (though Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of power which the Lord had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him for edification, and not to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10.) But if I plead for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity from <hi>railing</hi> and <hi>evil ſpeaking,</hi> the Text, I ſuppoſe, will bear me out in that.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially for the higher order of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> who ſucceed the Apoſtles: who have the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, not of the people only, fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence their name <hi>Epiſcopi;</hi> but of the Clergy too, and therefore termed <hi>Praelati:</hi> who are more then <hi>Rulers of the people,</hi> even <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Rulers of their Rulers alſo. I hope I may intercede in their behalf, that evil tongues may have leſs liberty to rail againſt ſuch; for ſuch the Text aims at directly. It was a High Prieſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42087:7"/>whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reviled here: and he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates clearly he would not have done it, had he known his eminence, that he was a <hi>Ruler of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon which two words, <hi>Ruler</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> ſo joyned, we have to obſerve, It excuſeth not any to ſay he is none of my Ruler whom I reproach, he hath no power over me. <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> had none over Saint <hi>Paul</hi> properly; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> rather, as an Apoſtle from Heaven, had power over <hi>Ananias.</hi> Yet if he be a Ruler of the people, ſpare him for the peoples ſake. They that in forraign Countreys raile upon Chriſtian Princes beyond the Seas, may do well to think upon this, as occaſion ſerves.</p>
            <p>And think alſo, if the Prince would be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born for the peoples ſake, then the more peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple he hath under him the more to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born: And the more removed from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſuch a Prince is, as being of nobler Birth, more excellent Education, Knowledge, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, Wiſdome, and Vertue, the more like God ſuch a Ruler is; and the leſs like one of the people, ſo much the leſſe to be tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and reproched by any of the people: yea, were the Reprochers Rulers themſelves, they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42087:7"/>may not ſpeak evil of their Fellow-Ruler, much leſſe of their Soveraign Ruler; for none of any ſort may be allowed to revile him. That will appear by the next point of our Diviſion, <hi>viz.</hi> Who are the parties reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that may not ſpeak evil. <hi>Non maledices tu,</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil;</hi> that is, neither thou <hi>Paul,</hi> nor any man.</p>
            <p>Not any man firſt: For this <hi>Non maledices</hi> is but a branch of <hi>Non dices falſum teſtimonium,</hi> which is the ninth Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſſe:</hi> and that is as univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal as <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> or <hi>ſteal,</hi> or <hi>commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</hi> So thou ſhalt not deprave or diſhonour thy Ruler by bad language, whoever thou art. <hi>Non reliquit hominem,</hi> ſaith the 105. <hi>Pſalm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.14.</note> ſpeaking of them that medled with the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, <hi>He ſuffered no man to doe them wrong, &amp;c.</hi> He will ſuffer no man to ſpeak wrong nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe that ſucceed the Patriarchs. <hi>Touch not mine Anoynted</hi> in that place binds up all hands.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15.</note> And <hi>Non maledices Principi,</hi> in this place, tieth up all tongues. <hi>Quis mittet manum,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lord's anoynted, and be gudtleſſe? Quis mittet linguam</hi> is as true alſo here, <hi>Who can
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42087:8"/>put forth his tongue againſt ſupreme Authority, and not be guilty of violating this precept? Non maledices, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not any, be he never ſo holy in the eyes of multitudes; much leſs they that are holy in their own eyes onely. Preciſe, ſanctified, illuminated brethren, ſo highly in favour with Heaven (as themſelves imagine) that they have a priviledge to cenſure every body elſe; as if they, forſooth, were the onely Saints pointed out in that ſpiritual man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. <hi>who judgeth all things, but he himſelf is judged of no man.</hi> Not any of theſe, how pure ſoever in their own ſight, are warranted to cenſure their equals, much leſſe their betters. <hi>Speak not evil one of another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>brethren,</hi> is S. <hi>James</hi> his precept to all men;
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.4</note> and, <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another man's ſervant?</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to any man. And if thou may'ſt not judge another man's ſervant, thou may'ſt not judge thine own Maſter, I am ſure, nor ſpeak evil of that ſupreme Power which God hath ordained to judge thee. Take heed: <hi>Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1</note> will infer, <hi>Let every tongue be ſubject alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was there any degree of men permitted to ſpeak evil againſt <hi>Moſes?</hi> nay, from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42087:8"/>to the loweſt, God teſtified his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt any that dared it. Not <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> thoſe counter-working Sorcerers, but for their foul tongues were plagued with foul botches, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.11. not <hi>Corah,</hi> a Levite, nor <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> Princes of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, but as they miſled others by their example,
<note place="margin">Numb. 16.32.</note> ſo were themſelves made examples by no common judgements. Not any of the people, were their complaints never ſo ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; not thoſe that lacked water at the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of <hi>Sin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 11.34.</note> nor thoſe that luſted for Fleſh at <hi>Kibroth Hattaavah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 11.3.</note> nor thoſe that complained of their way at <hi>Taberah;</hi> not any of theſe, were they few or many, eſcaped judgement: no, not all the many, all the Congregation ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered as one man againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 14.10.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the timorous ſpies, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.2. but did their penance for it in Peſtilence, in Fire, in the ſtings of Serpents, in ſundry kinds of death, till they were all conſumed, even more then 600000. men, excepting onely <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhuah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 14.30.</note> To omit thoſe that murmured upon the deſtruction of <hi>Corah</hi> (whoſe plague found no ſtop but the atonement of <hi>Aaron;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 16.50.</note>) not <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelf, though the brother of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 12.4.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42087:9"/>not <hi>Miriam,</hi> though his ſiſter, might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſo much as to whiſper againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> but ſtraight a cloud, a terrour, and a kindling of the Lord's anger. Num. 12.8. <hi>How is it, that ye were not afraid to ſpeak againſt my ſervant Moſes?</hi> So true is that of <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8. <hi>He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye.</hi> God will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a whiſper, nor a muttering, nor the breath of an unſavoury mock to come near his Anointed.</p>
            <p>Now if not the higheſt, if not <hi>Dathan,</hi> nor <hi>Corah,</hi> nor <hi>Miriam,</hi> nor <hi>Aaron,</hi> may open their lips againſt <hi>Moſes;</hi> how much leſſe the ſon of
<note n="*" place="margin">Lev. 24.11.</note> 
               <hi>Shelomith,</hi> one of the meaneſt of the people? If neither <hi>Nabal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.10.</note>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.3.</note> nor <hi>Achitophel,</hi> nor <hi>Abſalom</hi> may ſpeak evil of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.31.</note> how much leſſe
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei a Benjamite,</hi> or
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 20.1.</note> 
               <hi>Sheba</hi> the ſon of <hi>Bichri?</hi> How ill befits it to hear the worſt revile the beſt? baſe <hi>Therſites</hi> to rail upon royal <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 19.16.</note> 
               <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver-ſmith to mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt venerable <hi>Paul?</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> a prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Sophiſter, to prate againſt Saint <hi>John?</hi> Ignorance to deprave Learning? Rudeneſſe Experience? Youth to cenſure Age? illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Idiots to teach reverend Prelates? the off-ſcouring of the Rabble, the ſcumme of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42087:9"/>the Rout, to belch againſt God's Anointed, the Head of the Princes of the Tribes of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el? Proh dolor! Quis talia fando temperet à lacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis?</hi> What eyes can hold water? what eares endure the hearing?</p>
            <p>Intolerable this Abuſe, doubtleſſe; but eſpecially intolerable in two ſorts of men, the worſt and the beſt: The worſt, in regard of their meanneſſe, provoking indignation; and the beſt, in regard of their eminence, eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gaining belief. In the former ſort it argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth deſperate Preſumption; in the latter ſort Envie and Malice, ſiding with Ambition. For <hi>Shimei</hi> to reproch <hi>David</hi> brings certain vengeance on <hi>Shimei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King 2.46.</note> be <hi>David</hi> never ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful: For <hi>Achitophel</hi> to whiſper againſt his Soveraign, brings unavoidable ruine upon <hi>Achitophel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 17.13.</note> and upon <hi>Abſalom</hi> miſsled by his Councel,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.14.</note> be <hi>David</hi> never ſo low driven.</p>
            <p>Now though great the ſin of both, yet grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s, as one able to doe more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; one to whom more credit is given; one more obliged, and in his Maſter's boſom, able by revealing his ſecrets more to weaken him, and by his wiſdom to manage armies againſt him: fouler in <hi>Achitophel</hi> then in <hi>Shimei.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42087:10"/>And ſo it is in all Courtiers of the <hi>King's Family;</hi> in whom is fulfilled,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.9.</note> 
               <hi>The man that did eat of my bread hath lifted up his heel againſt me.</hi> And fouler yet,
<note place="margin">1 Kings 1.7.</note> if <hi>Abiathar</hi> ſhould fall off and ſide with the deſpiſers of <hi>David</hi> in his old age, drawing a ſcandal on the Prieſthood to boot, and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing numbers under colour of Religion. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly let bold Levites, the ſons of Thunder, that love to make the Pulpit a School of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, pretend what they will, no warrant have they from Heaven to traduce the Lord's Anointed. And ſo much greater is their crime, by how much more it concerns them to diſſwade all men from ſuch things. It is not the example of <hi>Nathan</hi> reproving <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.9.</note> nor of <hi>Elias</hi> threatning <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 21.21.</note> nor of <hi>Daniel</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.23.</note> will bear them out: nay, whe they can ſhew power to diſcover Secrets, as <hi>Nathan</hi> did, to doe Miracles, as <hi>Eliah,</hi> to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell things to come, as <hi>Daniel,</hi> then let them be bold with Princes, as they were. Meanwhile, look here upon S. <hi>Paul;</hi> S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that had greater Commiſsion then they can pretend any, that could doe as much as <hi>Elias,</hi> or <hi>Daniel,</hi> yet here acknowledging he went too far againſt <hi>Ananias.</hi> The caſe is worth inſiſting
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42087:10"/>on a little, and the order of our Diviſion now leads us to it.</p>
            <p>None may ſpeak evil of Rulers, no, though he be S. <hi>Paul.</hi> Why? Did not S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak evil? Was not his anſwer to <hi>Ananias</hi> a plain Curſe, with a Contumelie to boot? <hi>God ſhall ſmite thee:</hi> Is not that a Curſe? <hi>Thou whited wall:</hi> Is not that a Contumelie? The ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by thought it ſo, who preſently took up the Apoſtle, <hi>Revileſt thou God's High Prieſt?</hi> And we do not hear S. <hi>Paul</hi> denying that he reviled, but rather that he knew whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled; <hi>I wiſt not, brethren, that he was the High Prieſt.</hi> So an offence if it were in him, it was for lack of knowledge; as he ſaith elſewhere of his perſecution of the Church, <hi>I obtained mercy, becauſe I did it ignorantly,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13.</p>
            <p>But then, may Ignorance excuſe in ſuch a caſe? or can it be thought indeed, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was ignorant, ſo as not to know the High Prieſt? S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that was bred at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> expert in all Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes among the Jews, he to be ſuch a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to his own Nation, as not to know who ruled the Synagogue? Yes: 'Tis likely (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) the Apoſtle knew what the Jews cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42087:11"/>
               <hi>Ananias:</hi> But becauſe the High-Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>Aaron</hi> was now expired, 'twas void, and reſted in Chriſt; therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers like one that knew not <hi>Ananias,</hi> nor his Authority, intimating him but a private man. And therefore no ſuch peril in reviling one who was now no Ruler of the people.</p>
            <p>But this had been a worſe ſcorn then the other: and had S. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcovered any ſuch meaning, he had much more incenſed the ſtanders by, whom now he pacified; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in likelihood, carried not himſelf as one that meant to bereave <hi>Ananias</hi> of any honour, but to excuſe himſelf rather in not diſcerning his honour: he appeared, therefore, as one repenting and craving pardon; as if he ſhould ſay, Had I known him to be the High Prieſt, I would have known my duty better, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him no ſuch language.</p>
            <p>Excuſe S. <hi>Paul,</hi> therefore, as one truly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant who <hi>Ananias</hi> was: nor marvel if he were ignorant of him by face, though hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not by name. For S. <hi>Paul</hi> had now been many years abſent from <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and this meeting was not in the Synagogue, where he might diſtinguiſh the High Prieſt by his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42087:11"/>of ſitting, but in the Caſtle, where the chief Captain kept his Garriſon; and in likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the Jewiſh Rabbines ſtood not upon formalities there: So the high Prieſt by his ſitting S. <hi>Paul</hi> might not know. But, I pray, how could he chuſe but know him to be one of his Judges notwithſtanding? One of his Judges he himſelf confeſſeth him: For, <hi>Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou here to judge me according to Law, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt me to be ſmitten contrary to the Law?</hi> How is this then? May a Judge on the Bench be reviled, and not a High Prieſt? whereas the Law ſaith plainly, <hi>Thou ſhalt not curſe the Gods,</hi> that is, the <hi>Judges.</hi> And we have concluded neither ſuperiour nor inferiour Magiſtrates ſubject to our reviling. Which way will ye excuſe the Apoſtle then from tranſgreſsing the Law?</p>
            <p>Divers defences of S. <hi>Paul</hi> are here uſed by divers: but one of the beſt is S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s, That Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s anſwer to <hi>Ananias</hi> was not meant as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not as Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but a kind of free ſpeaking. To which liberty of ſpeech S. <hi>Paul</hi> was conſtrained, for <hi>Lyſias</hi> the chief Captain's ſake, there preſent. The day before, when the chief Captain went
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42087:12"/>about to ſcourge him,
<note place="margin">Act. 22.25.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> pleaded his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge as a <hi>Roman.</hi> Now when the High Prieſt commanded ſo baſely to ſmite him, ſhould he that would not take ſcourging at the Romans hands, take beating ſo patiently at the hand of the Jews, who were under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to the Romans, the chief Captain might well have thought him fooliſh and ſlaviſhly abject to the will of the Synagogue. Needful therefore for his credit's ſake, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould anſwer ſtoutly; and ſo he doth, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his reproof not to them that ſmote him, but to him that commanded him to be ſmitten. Howbeit, ſuch a reproof, as though it did not become him toward the High Prieſt, toward an inferiour Judge might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him well enough. S. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore being made to know his errour, is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to let the ſtanders by know his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and that ſuch freedome of ſpeech he would not have uſed, had he known the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of him to whom he ſpake, as being not ignorant that it is written in God's Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divers moral inferences might hence be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42087:12"/>gathered, which we have not time now to inſiſt on. As, That though Rulers forget their Duty, we are not to forget our Reverence. 2. That toward ſupreme Magiſtrates ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Honour is required. And That free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of ſpeech, which toward an inferiour Governour were but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Tongue-liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; toward a Superiour may be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, flat Contumely. 3. That it will not ſuffice to ſay, he was no good man, no lawfull Ruler we reviled, when we are judicially convented before him, and the people eſteem him ſo. 4. That Scripture-plea will not bear us out. S. <hi>Paul</hi> might have defended, <hi>God ſhall ſmite thee,</hi> from Pſal. 3.7. <hi>Thou ſmiteſt all thine enemies upon the cheek-bone:</hi> and, <hi>Thou whited wall,</hi> from Chriſt's own reſemblance of the Phariſees to <hi>whited ſepulchres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.27.</note> &amp;c. Yet he alledges no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for Contumely. S. <hi>Paul</hi> knows a ſtronger and a plainer Scripture againſt Contumely to Governours, namely, <hi>Non maledices Principi.</hi> 5. That if we have exceeded, through Paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Ignorance, in intemperate ſpeeches, we ſhould be ready to acknowledge our errour, with <hi>Neſciebam, fratres, I knew not what I did.</hi> 6. That evil ſpeaking, ſuch as ſcandals the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42087:13"/>hearers, in audience of the very ſame hearers would be recanted: &amp; That ſcandal is enough to make our ſpeeches evil, though otherwiſe in themſelves true &amp; juſtifiable. But this tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches upon the nature of evil ſpeaking it ſelf; and ſo leads us to the <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</hi> general of our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Having heard againſt whom evil may not be ſpoken, and the parties forbidden to ſpeak evil: come we in the next place to Evil ſpeaking it ſelf, the abuſe here forbidden, that we may ſhew what it is, and why forbidden.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What it is: And though evil ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be of many kinds, as Curſing, Railing, Slandering, Depraving; yet none are ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly here intended as thoſe evil ſpeakings which imply the party we ſpeak of to be evil. <hi>Dicere Principem malum, hoc eſt maledicere Principi,</hi> (ſaith one) To utter words, ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our Rulers to be evil, this is properly to ſpeak evil of Rulers.</p>
            <p>Why, but in ſo ſaying, perhaps we ſay true: And may we not ſpeak truth of our Rulers, affirming them to be as they are? Hath not the Prophet a <hi>Woe</hi> for them that call <hi>evil good,</hi> or <hi>good evil?</hi> Admit he hath; yet no warrant have we, for all that, to call that evil which is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42087:13"/>evil, unleſs charity lead us to it. For,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>Let all your things be done with charity</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle;) and charity will ſeldome lead us to ſpeak evil of our Neighbors, but of our lawful Governors never: For the very ſcandal of ſuch ſpeaking, though it be true, will out-weigh the benefit of knowing ſuch truth. Better it were by far for thoſe under authority, falſely to believe and ſpeak well of thoſe in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo they doe it ignorantly, then to believe or ſpeak evil of their Rulers never ſo know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of which appears grounded upon two of the ten Commandments, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Fifth and the Sixth. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi> firſt; and thy Ruler is a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In reference to his dignity, ſpeak not evil of him, though he deſerve it: For a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be he never ſo bad, ought not by his own children to be diſhonoured. And then, <hi>Doe no murther:</hi> ye cannot ſpeak evil of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate but ye help forward to Sedition, and Sedition is manifold Murther.</p>
            <p>But not to fall upon the reaſons why no evil ſpeaking, till ye have ſeen what: note, that evil ſpeaking in general is by ſome divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42087:14"/>
               <hi>Judicative</hi> and <hi>Optative; Judicative,</hi> affirming evil, and <hi>Optative,</hi> wiſhing evil: both are in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s anſwer to <hi>Ananias.</hi> Some divide it into evil ſpeaking in preſence; that is <hi>Contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.7.</note> as <hi>Shimei</hi> to <hi>David, Come forth thou man of bloud:</hi> and evil ſpeaking in abſence, as <hi>Miriam</hi> ſpake againſt <hi>Moſes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 12.1.</note> that is <hi>Detraction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fitteſt diviſion for our purpoſe ſeems drawn from the Text, as it ſtands in the old Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Ruler of thy people.</hi> Where the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth Vilifying, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting; and the latter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Railing, or Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Which two ſeem to point us to the two Fountains from whence all evil ſpeaking proceeds, <hi>viz.</hi> Wrath, or Envy: Vilifying or Detracting, the fruit of Envy; Railing and Curſing, of Wrath or Malice. One of theſe two moves in evil tongues, either Wrath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have received ſome evil from our Rulers; or Envy, becauſe we think they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive too much good. And as Envy is more frequent then Wrath, ſo Detraction more abounds then Railing or Curſing.</p>
            <p>To touch upon them in order. Railing or Contumely ſeems that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42087:14"/>with here: his reproching <hi>Ananias</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears as proceeding from ſudden Wrath in his own vindication. Now from Wrath are numbred four kinds of evil ſpeaking, <hi>viz.</hi> Contumely, Malediction, Whiſpering, and Slandering: The two former, Contumely and Malediction, proceeding from Wrath in the heat of it, furious at firſt kindling; the two latter, Whiſpering and Slandering, from Wrath cooled and digeſted into Hatred and Malice.</p>
            <p>Contumely is defined to be a reproching any to his face, by words or deeds diſgracing his honour; as the Phariſees to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">John 8.48.</note> 
               <hi>Say we not well thou art a Samaritane, and haſt a devil?</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Judah</hi> to <hi>Jeremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt falſely, the Lord our God hath not ſent thee;</hi> but <hi>Baruch the ſonne of Neriah ſets thee on.</hi> No light crime ſuch Contumely; for the leaſt degrees of it are heavily ſentenced in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: <hi>Whoſo ſhall ſay to his brother, Raca, ſhall be liable to a Council;</hi> and <hi>he that ſhall ſay, Thou fool, in danger of hell-fire.</hi> Contumely differs from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lediction, becauſe it may be real as well as verbal; in deed, no leſs then word: as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt deſcribes ſome wagging their heads at
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42087:15"/>our Lord's Paſsion,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.7.</note> ſhooting out their lips, gaping with their mouths; and yet that was Contumely. Whereas Malediction is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be a vehement wiſhing of evil with words of imprecation, in the bitterneſs of <hi>ſoul;</hi> and ſo is but in word at moſt, if it go farther then the heart. Beſides, Malediction aims at the Perſon, but Contumely ſtrikes at his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And of the two, Contumely is the fouler crime, as it is abler to doe more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief: for Malediction (take away Scandal) cannot hurt him much on whom it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, if he deſerve it not; inaſmuch as Curſes cauſeleſs light upon the head of him that utters them, and wound the party curſing more then the party curſed.</p>
            <p>Both theſe, as well Contumely as Maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, are ten-fold worſe againſt our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours then againſt our Equals: inſomuch that <hi>Shimei</hi> for his contumely againſt <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 2.46.</note> was juſtly rewarded with capital puniſhment at length: And, <hi>whoſo revileth or curſeth father or mother, let him die the death,</hi> ſaith the old Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.17.</p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid, Neither of theſe are much to be charged upon our times. I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42087:15"/>would they were not, and that in the moſt wicked manner. A Contumely there is by Libelling, as Schoolmen note: For three kinds of it there are in all. 1. Contumely by word in audience of the party reviled; as when the children reproched <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Come up thou bald head.</hi> 2. Contumely by foul language in the ears of ſuch as may carry it to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reviled; as when <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> railed upon <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in the hearing of the Jewiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors.
<note place="margin">2 King. 18.29.</note> 3. Contumely by Libelling; as when <hi>Sanballat</hi> ſent an open Letter to <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> taxing him with an intent to be King, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6.6. Of the three this of Libelling is the worſt kind of contumely in many reſpects: for it ſpreads wider, wounds deeper, laſts longer, ſmarts ſorer, and is both Contumely and Detraction mingled in one. Inaſmuch as the Author hides his head, 'tis Detraction; as it comes to the libelled parties eares, 'tis Contumely: So 'tis allied to Malice and Envy, to Murther and to Theft both. What ſhall be ſaid to this impudent, yet corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeping villany.? this murthering worth and honour, as it were by the ſhot of a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll in the dark? this ſtealing the jewel of a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42087:16"/>good name by a hand inviſible? but what the wiſe man ſaith of a friend turned enemy,
<note place="margin">Ecclus 37.3.</note> 
               <hi>0 wicked imagination! whence cameſt thou in to cover the earth with deceit?</hi> Doubtleſs, if it be ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous to ſpeak evil of Rulers by detraction in abſence, 'tis much worſe to ſpeak evil to Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers by contumely to their face; and worſe yet to write evil of our Rulers, which is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil as well as ſpeaking, and was ſeldom puniſhed in any well governed Monarchy with leſs then Death or Mutilation.</p>
            <p>Nor may we excuſe our Times from the other crime of Malediction; onely whereas Curſing is eſteemed a fruit of Wrath, by way of Revenge for Injury, Experience in ſome of our people ſheweth it is otherwiſe now and then: they can curſe <hi>gratis,</hi> and heap with Maledictions the beſt of Governors, for no injury at all ever done them; fulfilling that of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.5. <hi>Thus have they rewarded me evil for good,
<note place="margin">Pſal.69.4:</note> &amp;c They that hate me without a cauſe are more in number then the hairs of my head.</hi> 'Tis true, that Curſing is properly a fruit of Wrath rather then Malice. But what ſay we to Wrath ingendered of Malice and Hatred? and that Hatred upon no ground but Envy?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42087:16"/>ſuch as the Phariſees hatred and wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Saviour, who never did them evil? Such wrathful and ſpightful Malediction is, without doubt, the worſt that can be.</p>
            <p>To leave Contumely and Curſing: there follow Whiſpering and Slandering; fruits of Wrath too, but of Wrath cooled and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted into Malice. Of the twain, the Whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perer is ſomewhat worſe then the Slanderer: For the Whiſperer wears the habit of a friend, and under that viſor deprives us of our friends. A ſmooth-fac'd Murtherer, a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked-tongu'd Serpent, a two-edg'd Sword, as <hi>Bernard</hi> calls him, relating to one friend what may moſt exaſperate him againſt another, &amp; ſo poiſoning them both: Licking and biting, ſtroaking and wounding, ſometimes in one breath.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus. 28.13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Curſe the whiſperer and double-tongued,</hi> ſaith the ſon of <hi>Syrach; for ſuch have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many that were at peace.
<note place="margin">Ver. 16.</note> Whoſo hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens to it ſhall never find rest, nor ever dwell quietly.</hi> Amongſt thoſe whom God hates, the chiefeſt is he that <hi>ſoweth diſcord amongst brethren,</hi> Prov. 6.19. If he that robs us of our Fame or Honour be ſuch a hateful enemy; how much more he that bereaves us of our
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42087:17"/>Friends, for whoſe ſake we deſire Fame and Honour? Abandoned therefore above all other be the Tale-bearer and the Whiſperer, whoſe words are as the piercings of a ſword. Take away the <hi>Tale-bearer, and Contention will ceaſe,</hi> Prov. 26.20.</p>
            <p>Next after the Whiſperer goeth the Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer; a vice near allied to the Devil: from whence <hi>Satan</hi>'s name <hi>Diabolus,</hi> viz. from falſe accuſing and ſlandering the Brethren. Upon the Slanderer all the people were to beſtow a general curſe. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.24. <hi>Curſed be he that ſmites his neighbour ſecretly.</hi> And God himſelf in <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.16, &amp;c. ſmites him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably; <hi>If a falſe witneſs riſe up againſt any, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie what is wrong, inquiry ſhall be made, and ye ſhall doe unto the falſe witneſs as he had thought to have done unto his brother. Thou ſhalt not raiſe a falſe report, nor joyn hands with the wicked, to be an unrighteous witneſs,</hi> Exod 23.1. A moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous evil, whereby the faireſt Vertue in the world may be blaſted at a diſtance, undone in ſecret, and not know who hurteth it. If it ſpread in multitudes, it quickly makes up that three-fold Evil the Wiſe-man ſo trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at, and prayed againſt, <hi>viz. The ſlander of a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42087:17"/>City, The gathering together of an unruly multitude, and a falſe Accuſation: All theſe are worſe then death,</hi> Ecclus. 26.5. The Slanderer differs from the Whiſperer, in that he is fouler mouth'd, and appears more like an enemy, and commonly hath the Whiſperer for his fore-runner. Let the Whiſperer aggravate a true matter, and blemiſh it with an odious colour; the Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer ſhall blacken it more with lying, and augment it with manifold addition. Let the Whiſperer ſay to day, <hi>Moſes</hi> favours an <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> woman; the Slanderer will ſay to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Moſes</hi> deſpiſeth his own Nation, and prefers in his love any before them.</p>
            <p>This for evil ſpeaking from Wrath and from Malice. But more abundant are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies from Envy, which in general are four-fold alſo; that is, <hi>Detraction</hi> and <hi>Murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Complaining</hi> and <hi>Deriſion;</hi> whereto ſome adde <hi>Depravation.</hi> Two of which are more common againſt all ſorts of men, <hi>viz. Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and <hi>Deriſion:</hi> and two more peculiar againſt Governours, to wit, <hi>Murmuring</hi> and <hi>Complaining.</hi> None of theſe are ſo properly the fruits of Envy, but that they proceed alſo, many times, from Hatred and Malice.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:42087:18"/>
            <p> For Detraction firſt; it is one of the moſt reigning vices in this laſt age of the world, and moſt properly condemned in this Text, which is read in many Tranſlations, <hi>Diis non detrabes,</hi> Thou ſhalt not detract from the Gods, nor revile Rulers. Detraction is by <hi>Aquinas</hi> defined to be <hi>Denigratio famae alienae per verba occulta,</hi> A blackening or beſpotting our neighbour's fame by clandeſtine ſpeeches in his abſence; called therefore Backbiting: And differs from Slander, inaſmuch as Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is alwayes in abſence; but Slander may be in preſence. Slander is evermore falſe; but Detraction may report but what is true. And five wayes, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> noteth, may Detraction go to work. 1. By inventing a Slander or falſe Report: As the Phariſees,
<note place="margin">Mat 9.34.</note> when they affirmed our Saviour to <hi>caſt out Devils by Beelzebub.</hi> 2. By aggravating a true matter:
<note place="margin">Gen. 31.1.</note> As <hi>Laban</hi>'s ſons of <hi>Jacob; Jacob hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away all that was our Father's, and from our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath gotten this glory.</hi> 3. By revealing an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour before hidden:
<note place="margin">Gen. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> As <hi>Cham,</hi> when he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Father's nakedneſſe. 4. By depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an action well meant: As <hi>Doeg,</hi> when he traduced the High-Prieſt for relieving <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.9.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:42087:18"/>5. By diminiſhing or concealing the <hi>good</hi> things in our neighbour, and uttering onely what we think <hi>bad:</hi> As <hi>Ahab</hi> of <hi>Micaiah; I hate him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 22.8.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he never propheſieth good unto me, but evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the uſual wayes of Detraction: And by this, ye may perceive it comprehends not ſlanderous and falſe rumours onely; but ſuch as are true likewiſe, if uttered with an intent to hurt our neighbour's fame. For, as the ninth Commandment is broken by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable witneſs, as well as falſe witneſs, becauſe Charity is the fulfilling of the Law: ſo the Detractor, in ſpoiling his neighbour's ſame, is not excuſed, though he ſay true, for we are not allowed to hurt any by word any more then deed. And is Defamation no hurt, think ye? What wiſe man eſteems not his Fame more precious then his Wealth? And is he a Thief, that robs his neighbour's purſe; and he none, that robs him of his good name? Plead not truth therefore in defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our brethren; but remember Truth and Peace ought to go together.
<note place="margin">zach. 8.19.</note> 
               <hi>Love the Truth and Peace</hi> (ſaith <hi>Zacharie.</hi>) And Peace will never abide detracting from our equals; much leſs our Superiors. <hi>Charity</hi> wil hide ſuch
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42087:19"/>truths;
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.8.</note> for Love covers a multitude of ſins.</p>
            <p>After Detraction followeth Murmuring: A vice too frequent in the common ſort againſt their Governours: As faſt as any Calamities befall them, their Rulers bear the blame of it preſently. Let any Scarcity, or decay of Trade, any Contagion or Plague from God's hand, or through their own miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour, light upon them, all is laid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly upon the ſcore of their Leaders. If the Iſraelites want fleſh, or any varieties they long for, who but <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> hear ill for it ſtraight?
<note place="margin">Numb. 20 5.</note> 
               <hi>Why have ye brought us into this evil place? Here is neither fields nor vineyards, and our ſoul is dried away with this light bread.</hi> Yea, though no evils befall us, if others receive as much good, it ſets a murmuring tongue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barking very often. Thus the Labourers in the Vineyard murmure againſt the good man that hired them;
<note place="margin">Mat. 20.12.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe have wrought but one hour, and thou haſt made them equall to us,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Luke 15.29.</note> And the Prodigal's elder brother; <hi>So many years have I ſerved thee, and thou never ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me a kid.</hi> A ſervile vice this Murmuring; and therefore ſo frequent in ſervile and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar diſpoſitions. It is the property of bad
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42087:19"/>ſervants to be alwayes murmuring: and it is the juſtice of good Maſters to afflict them the more for it. So God deals with murmuring people, and never fails to ſcourge that Nation where this ſin abounds.</p>
            <p>To Murmuring ye may adde Complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<note place="margin">Jude 16.</note> 
               <hi>S. Jude</hi> well couples them together: <hi>Theſe are murmurers, complainers, walkers after their own luſts, &amp;c.</hi> The difference between both is, That the Murmurer takes on in his own behalf, becauſe ſomewhat is wanting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: but the Complainer he is zealous in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of others; finds fault That Honours and Offices are not beſtowed upon ſuch as deſerve them beſt; That able Preachers are undone for Ceremonies, while men of worſe Giſts and Lives are countenanced. As if diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Supreme Authority were not ſo much the greater, by how much the ſmaller the things, &amp; on ſlighter reaſon refuſed. Or as if thoſe that ſwallowed Oaths of Non-adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Covenants of Rebellion without ſcruple of conſcience, were to be regarded while they pretend conſcience againſt <hi>Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</hi> Others complain, that old ſervants are forgotten, and they that have ſuffered moſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42087:20"/>are leaſt regarded. 'Tis hard pleaſing men of this humour. <hi>Remember, Lord,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>how I do hear in my boſom the rebukes of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, where with thine enemies have blaſphemed thee, and ſlandered the foot-ſteps of thine Anointed.</hi> Let ſuch complainers have the guidance of affairs in their own hands, and they would ſpeedily take away all Grievances, and mend all that is amiſs. Yea, juſt like the Reformers in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> or ſome others in this Kingdom that took after them, who pretending Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, inſtead of one abuſe rectified, quickly brought in an hundred.</p>
            <p>Worſe then the Complainer is the Derider, or Depraver, the fourth and laſt ſort of evil ſpeakers, that can turn the moſt venerable things into matter of ſcorn; can ſcoff at the ſacred Ceremonies of Religion, as <hi>Michal</hi> ſcoffed at <hi>David</hi> dancing in his linen Ephod.
<note place="margin">2 Sam, 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>The eye that mocks at his father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30.17.</note> 
               <hi>and deſpiſeth his mother, let the Ravens of the valleys pick it out, and the young Eagles devour it.</hi> How theſe kind of ſins provoke the patience of heaven, ye may ſee by thoſe children that mocked <hi>Eliſha.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 2.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the Derider ye may ſet the Depraver, who interprets all occurrences in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42087:20"/>the worſt ſenſe:
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.29.</note> like <hi>Saul</hi> the Tyrant, who imagined <hi>David</hi>'s Victories over the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> ſo many ſecret ſteps to the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael; David</hi>'s courteous and affable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.15.</note> his art to win the hearts of the people;
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 20.30.</note> His obſequiouſneſs to <hi>Jonathan,</hi> a kind of cunning to ſave himſelf, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Saul</hi>'s projects. Like Depravations abound with ſome of our people, who interpret Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of Divine Worſhip, a ſtinting the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Spirit; Appointing a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent length of publick Prayers, a Devourer of Preaching; Reviving ancient and decent Ceremonies, a ſtep to bring in Popery. We owe the beginning of all our late bloudy Wars to Depravations of this ſort. Let ſuch kind of falſe gloſſes and abuſive paintings be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, ye may ſee by the common practice of ſubtil Lawyers, how eaſie it is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the faireſt face, and to make the beſt cauſe look like the worſt. There cannot be a worſe Requital of the great pains of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and their care for our ſafety, then thus to miſ-conſtrue their endevours for our good; and while we enjoy peace and plenty under them, for bread, on this manner, to return them ſtones.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:42087:21"/>
            <p> Ye have ſeen this Evil ſpeaking againſt Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers what it is, and which be the uſuall kinds of it. Adde now ſome reaſons why it is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, and we have done. And we need go no farther then our Text to begin. They are called in <hi>Exodus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe they bare the burthen of the people:
<note place="margin">Num. 11.14.</note> 
               <hi>I am not able to bear all this people alone</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes.</hi>) Do they bear, with ſo much love, our infirmities? and ſhall we, full of ſo much ſpight, heap them with calumnies? Then they are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods, as executing his judgements, ſitting in his Throne, and placed neareſt to him, as his Deputies. So that whereas Railing againſt one of the people is but Obloquy; ſpeaking evil of our Rulers is a kind of Blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>And marvel not at it.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> For if <hi>he that reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God,</hi> he that depraves lawful Powers, depraves God's Ordinance too. Hence is it that <hi>Moſes</hi> tells the rebellious, Your murmurings are not againſt us,
<note place="margin">Num. 16.11.</note> but againſt the Lord: <hi>And what is Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, that ye murmure againſt him? Thou and all thy company with thee (o Corah) are gathered againſt the Lord.</hi> And ſo are all that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine againſt their rightful Governours. If Rebellion of the hand, if Reſiſting be damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42087:21"/>neither is Rebellion of the tongue, nor Depraving excuſable. Againſt the Ordinance of God they are both alike.</p>
            <p>Againſt the Ordinance of God? Yea, and againſt Nature too. For what more unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, then to repay evil for good? and where all the Honours and Rewards we can deviſe are but a ſcant Compenſation, there to return ill language, Diſobedience and Contradiction? to wound their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Renown, in whoſe good report conſiſts our own? to render for benefits ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable, wounds incurable? For no art nor diligence can make amends for defaming Magiſtrates. Private Obloquies may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted, and ſome reſtitution made: But De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions againſt Rulers ſpread beyond all power of recalling, and flie into foreign Countreys, and blemiſh their reputation, not onely during life, but after death; deceiving not the preſent age alone, but poſterity alſo; and making whole Nations, by their own tongues, inſtruments of their own miſeries.</p>
            <p>The Defamers therefore of Rulers are not onely <hi>hominum,</hi> but <hi>humanitatis hoſtes,</hi> as one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them; not enemies of men alone, but ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of all man-kind. For every Reproch
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42087:22"/>of thoſe in Authority is a puſhing againſt Authority; and every puſhing againſt Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, a ſtep to bring in Anarchy; and Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is the worſt kind of Tyranny, turning a peaceable Order of men into the Confuſion of wild beaſts.</p>
            <p>No wonder if contempt of Magiſtracy therefore be indicted as a breaker of all God's <hi>ten Commandments.</hi> Of the whole firſt Table. For who ſhall reſtrain Atheiſm againſt the <hi>firſt Commandment,</hi> keep out Superſtition againſt the <hi>ſecond,</hi> puniſh Blaſphemy and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury againſt the <hi>third,</hi> or uphold the publick Worſhip of God according to the <hi>fourth,</hi> when Magiſtracy is down? And of the ſecond Table no leſs. For if publick Fathers of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey loſe their honour, how can private Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents expect any from their children, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>fifth Commandment?</hi> Who ſhall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Murther againſt the <hi>ſixth,</hi> Adultery againſt the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> Theſt againſt the <hi>eighth,</hi> or Slander againſt the <hi>ninth?</hi> Nay, what greater Theſt, then by Slander to rob Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of their power, and our Countrey of their protection, both at once? Who ſhall defend private men in their right and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and keep off him that againſt the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42087:22"/>
               <hi>tenth Commandment</hi> covets and would invade his Neighbour's poſſeſsions, when Princes cannot be quiet in their own poſſeſsions?</p>
            <p>So of all the Commandments in both Tables, the depraver of Magiſtrates is guilty. Guilty alſo of the deſtruction of multitudes, of kindling Wild-fire, of ſpreading Leproſie, of diſperſing Peſtilence. For no ſuch Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire as the tongues of Detractors kindle: No ſuch Leproſie as proceeds from their foul breath: No ſuch contagious Peſtilence as their mouths ſcatter: No ſuch Aegyptian darkneſs as they would bring in. The good name and vertues of Magiſtrates ſhine like a Lamp far and near; like the Moon in a clear night, or like the Sun in the firmament. The obſcuring of their light by foul Aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is like eclipſing the great Luminaries of Heaven, caſting horrour and amazement on the world.</p>
            <p>Adde to this the wofull Conſequences, too freſhly bleeding in late experience; no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience made of reviling Rulers, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly none of riſing againſt Rulers; none of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, Sacriledge, Oppreſsion, Murther; pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sword out of the Prince's hand, and ſheathing it in one anothers bowels. All
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42087:23"/>through the miſchief of virulent tongues, which with their peſtilent air ſmother the Truth, overwhelming both Prince and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a dark ſtorm of Sedition, and inſatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Common ſort with rage and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; not caring, like mad dogs, whom they ſnarle and ſnap at, whom they miſchief or undoe; perſecuting Innocence many times to death, and after death; not thinking it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough they have murthered good men in their Perſons, unleſs they murther them in their Fame alſo to all poſterity.</p>
            <p>Rightly therefore are perverſe tongues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to teeth, and the Detractor called a Back-biter.
<note place="margin">Cal. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>But if ye bite and de your one another, take beed ye be not conſumed one of another.</hi> Elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <hi>David</hi> terms ſuch a tongue,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 57 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſpears,</hi> and <hi>arrows,</hi> and a <hi>ſharp ſword.</hi> For nothing cuts like it, nor any ſuch ready inſtrument of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The tongue of Detractors it was that nailed Chriſt to his Croſs.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.18.</note> The tongue of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eg,</hi> that murthered fourſcore and five Prieſts in one day. Though <hi>Doeg</hi>'s hand were bloudy alſo,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 52.2.</note> yet <hi>David</hi> complains of the tongue, ſaith nothing of the hand.
<note place="margin">Num 21.6.</note> The tongues of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers,
<note place="margin">Num. 16.33.</note> that called in fiery Serpents. The tongues of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42087:23"/>made the earth open her mouth. Obſerve what a fearful judgement, and how all the four Elements ſeemed to abandon thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilers of Magiſtrates! Below the face of the Earth they ſunk, that they might not pollute the very ground they trode on. From the Air they were excluded, that their breath might not poiſon the air. Beneath the Waters they deſcended, that their carkaſes might not defile the waters. Below the earth and the depth of it, down to the center they were plunged, down to hell it ſelf, that the earth might not be diſhonoured with their grave. O the horrid guilt of muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous tongues, that could deſerve ſuch a judgement! What need more be added, when Chriſt brandeth the Phariſees ſlander with ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Mar. 3.29, 30.</note> and makes the fouleſt of all crimes but a ſin of the tongue; the onely ſin that ſhall accompany the damned in Hell, where they ſhall blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, and rail, and curſe themſelves, and the higher Powers, when they can doe no more.</p>
            <p>Let all theſe things move us to beware of ſo ungrateful, ſo unnatural a ſin, as to revile and ſpeak evil of thoſe whoſe whole care and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42087:24"/>ſtudy day and night is onely to doe us good; to blaſt and deprave their good names, who defend us and our names, and all we have elſe, from injury. Be ſo far from evil-ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch, that we neither endure to hear evil of them from others, nor to think or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine any in our hearts, or give credit to ill ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours we hear with our ears: But inure our ſelves quite contrary, to think and ſpeak the beſt, to put the faireſt colours we can upon all that our Rulers doe; to defend their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and honour them as our Parents; ever bleſsing and praying for them, That God would deliver them from the peril of all wicked tongues, and more wicked hands; And though undeſervedly ſometimes they hear ill, that they may never be diſcouraged from doing well; nor by the unthankfulneſs of ſome few envious people, be withdrawn from loving and caring for all their people: But that Rulers and people may be happy one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and being mutually praiſed and bleſſed one of another, may receive the bleſsing of Peace internal and external here, till they be received into the bleſsing of Peace eternall hereafter. <hi>To which,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
